Guide to the Dean of Students records, 1968-1992 RG0046
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Dean of Students records
1968-1992
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
George Washington University. Office of the Dean of Students
RG0046
27.25 Linear Feet
Collection includes student surveys, annual reports, correspondence, memos, manuals, and committee files.
Restrictions on Access
Series 4 and 5 are closed to research for 25 years from date of record creation.
Access to student records is governed by the federal Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA), which protects the privacy of student education records. Student records in series 2 and 3 are closed for 100 years from date of record creation.
Acquisition Information
Materials acquired through transfers from the Associate Vice President and Dean of Students.
Historical Note
The Associate Vice President and Dean of Students of The George Washington University reports to the Senior Vice President for Student and Academic Support Services (in 2003 the name was changed from Vice President for Student and Academic Support Services). Before 1989 the Dean of Students was under the Vice President for Student Affairs.
The Dean has responsibility for oversight of housing and residential facilities for the Foggy Bottom and Mount Vernon campuses and the Columbia Plaza Housing Program. The Dean enforces University policies - Code of Student Conduct, alcohol policy, sexual harassment, residential community conduct guidelines and administrative policies, etc.
The Dean provides administrative and personal assistance and referral regarding student medical or mental health problems. Assistance includes: withdrawals, notification of appropriate administrative staff and consultations with medical personnel.
The Dean handles civil rights and discrimination complaints, responds to federal and state agencies, ADA, sexual harassment, Drug Free Schools and Community Act, and other laws and regulations as they affect students. The Dean also oversees substance abuse prevention strategies and interventions with student substance abusers.
The office publishes the Guide to Student Rights and Responsibilities each year.
N.B. This history note was written in 2005
Collection Scope and Content
Materials in this collection include student surveys, annual reports, correspondence, memos, manuals, and committee files. They range in date from 1968 to 1992, and were transferred to the University Archives by the Dean of Students. Note: Not all series are processed. Ask staff for assistance.
Collection Organization
Organized into six series: One series titled Publications and five series titled Office files.
Students; Student activities; Campuses; Housing; Foggy Bottom (Washington, D.C.); Sexual harassment; Policies and institutions; Washington (D.C.); Students, Foreign; Reports and studies; George Washington University; Trachtenberg, Stephen Joel; George Washington University. Mount Vernon Campus
- Publications, 1974-1992; RG0046 Series 1; 0.25 Linear feet (Box 1, Box SHARED 2)
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains parent's handbooks and the Faculty Guide to Student Services published by the Dean of Students Office. They range in date from 1984-92.
  - Faculty Guide to Student Services, 1986-1988 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Parents Handbook, 1984-1992 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Student Conduct Guidebook and Parent Handbooks, 1974, 1982-1992; Series 1 (Box SHARED 2, Folder 2)
- Office files, 1984-1988; RG0046 Series 2; 6 Linear feet
  Conditions Governing Access
  Access to student records is governed by the federal Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA), which protects the privacy of student education records. Student records are closed for 100 years from date of record creation..
  This series contains student surveys and exit interviews dated 1984-88.
  - Graduating Senior Surveys, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Graduating Outcomes Surveys, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Alumni Outcome Surveys, 1987-1988 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Alumni Outcome Surveys, 1987-1988 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Essays on GWU, 1984-1985 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Withdrawing/Non-returning student surveys, 1986-1988 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Exit Interviews, 1984-1988 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Office files, 1971-1987; RG0046 Series 3; 3 Linear feet
  This series contains annual reports, career services center records, and disabled student services reacords. This material is dated 1971-87
- Office files, 1968-1988; RG0046 Series 4; 1.5 Linear feet
  This series contains annual reports, the Human Relations Act of GW, equal opportunity program report, and student affairs staff manual. The material is dated 1968-88.
  - Human Relations Act of the GWU, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Vice President for Student Affairs Goals and Objectives (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Dean of Students Office Functions, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    General note
    missing
  - Dean of Students Office Annual Report, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Missing
  - Annual Reports, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Educational Opportunity Program, Counselors Center, and Career Services Center
  - Annual Reports, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    International Services, Student Health Services, and Disabled Student Services
  - Parents Handbook, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Student Affairs Staff Manual, University Counseling Center, and Internship Program, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Statement of Student Rights and Responsibilities, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Annual Reports, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Creative Process Arts Fair, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Computers and Society, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Building JJ Report, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Computers and Society, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Roots Residential Program, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Living Learning, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - The Creative Process Building JJ (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Faculty Guide to Student Services, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Utopian Ideals, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - EOP Annual Report, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Office files, 1950-1990; RG0046 Series 5; 15 Linear feet
  This series contains residence hall association records, student organizations/government, mortar board, committee records, Educational Opportunity Program (EOP), judicial system history, greek life, surveys/evaluations, international student services, President Trachtenberg speeches, and information about the Thurston Hall fire. This material is dated 1950-90.
  - Student Rights, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Residence Hall Association, 1985-1990 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Program Board, 1975-1990 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Student Organization, 1975-1990 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Political Activities (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Pres. Appeals, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Security (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Forgery, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Disruptions, 01/1969 --12/1980 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Computer Fraud, 01/1984 --12/1989 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Judicial Affairs, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Compliance Regulations, 1985-1990 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Grievence Committee, 1985-1990 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - International Services, 1985-1990 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Student Health Insurance, 1985-1990 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous Division Files, 1985-1990 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - EOP, 1985-1990 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - MSSC, 1985-1990 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Mortar board, 1950-1980 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Judicial committee, 1970-1988 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Academic Dishonesty, 1970-1988 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Student Organizations, 1970-1988 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Student Government, 1970-1988 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Living and Learning Programs, 1983-1984 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - EOP (Educational Opportunity Program), 1970-1988 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - EOP Advisory Committee, 1970-1985 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - EOP Historical Development and Time Line, 1968-1990 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Judicial System (History), 1970-1985 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Code of Conduct and Revisions, 1980-1988 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - V.P and Treasurer, 1975-1985 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Evidence (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Individual Rights, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - .Committee, 1988-1990 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous Conferences, 1980-1985 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Housing and Residence Life, 1985-1990 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Judicial Affairs, 1988-1990 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Minority Affairs, 1988-1990 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - EOP, 1988-1990 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - D.C. Woks, 1988-1990 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Orientation, 1988-1990 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Greek Life, 1988-1990 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Academic Dishonesty, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - University Counseling Center, 1980-1990 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1988-1990 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Committees and Conferences, 1985-1990 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Budget Advisory Team, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Student Health Service, 1980-1986 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Academic Assistance Projects (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Xerox, 1990 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Development (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - MLK Convocation, 1989 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - AIDS, 1985-1990 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Greek Life, 1985-1990 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Orientation, 1985-1990 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Student Organizations, 1985-1990 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - University Policies, 1985-1990 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Recreational Sports, 1985-1990 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Student Health Service-Immunizations, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Surveys and Evaluations, 1979-1980 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - International Student Services, 1984-1988 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Trachtenberg Speeches, 1988 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - V.P. Bill Smith, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Sexual Harassment (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Rapid Rescue (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Thruston Fire, 1980 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Publications (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Withdrawals, 1980 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Disabled Student Services, 1990 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Alumni Trustee (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Dos Budget (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Compliance (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Hatchet Clippings, 1987-1990 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Judicial System, 1970-1989 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Alcohol Education, 1987 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Hazing, 1988 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - President, 1975-1990 (Box 10, Folder 7)
- Office files, 1968-1988; RG0046 Series 6; 1.5 Linear feet
  This series contains departmental files for subjects such as student and alumni career services, Chinese students, student activities, international services, dean of students, and division organization. This material is dated 1968-88.